A Guide to the Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers, 1884-1964.
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers 1884-1964
Special Collections, Kegley Library
1983.1
54 folders..
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Beverly Repass Hoch in 1983.
Biographical Information
A great-grandson of Irish emigrant James McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., was born to Randal and Cynthia Elizabeth McGavock of Max Meadows, Virginia in 1856. Randal lived in his father's (Hugh McGavock) homestead and was a prosperous farmer. Jacob Cloyd McGavock continued the family legacy of farming. In 1883 he married Amanda Billups of Norfolk, Virginia. Several years later the couple and their growing family moved into the family home in Max Meadows, Virginia.
Amanda Billups McGavock was the daughter of prominent Norfolk businessman Cealy Billups. Upon his death in 1910, Amanda assumed ownership of several residential and commercial properties. Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and Randal McGavock essentially supervised the management of these valuable properties with assistance of several rental agencies in Norfolk.
Amanda suffered from what her doctors termed a nervous disorder. Evidently she sought relief from her illness with morphine. She continued this habit for some time amidst the advice of one of her doctors, Dr. W. S. Sayers of Roanoke, Virginia. She spent much time in hospitals and clinics in Richmond, Virginia and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. She died in 1915.
Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and Amanda McGavock reared five children. Their eldest, Eulalie Billups McGavock, tragically died in 1903. Their eldest son, Randal, moved to Norfolk, Virginia where he worked in his grandfather's farming implement business. He married Hazel Stone of Norfolk, Virginia.
Born in 1890, their son Cecil Billups McGavock assisted his father with farming after his education at Emory and Henry College and Virginia Polytechnic Institute. In 1911 he married Mamie Claiborne of Montgomery, Alabama and in September 1912 became the father of Cecil Billups McGavock Jr. Cecil and Mamie eventually separated; she lived in Charlottesville while Cecil worked for many years in South Hill, Virginia. He died in 1960.
Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. was born in 1893 and attended school at Massanutten Academy, S. R. Crockett's school in Crockett, Virginia, and Fishburne Military Academy. He settled in Max Meadows, Virginia after a stint of working in Detroit, Michigan. He married Cynthia Painter of Alabama; he later remarried Byrd Pendleton in 1967 and remained in Wythe County, Virginia farming. He also served on the Board of Supervisors. He died in 22 January 1989.
Ezra Summers McGavock, the youngest child of Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and Amanda Billups McGavock, was born in 1897. He attended Hampden-Sidney College and Union Theological Seminary. He served Presbyterian churches in rural Bland County before moving to larger areas in Virginia and West Virginia. He first married Mary Haynes in the early 1920s; she died in 1965. He then married Marjory Deane Davis Cornett in 1969; she died in 1977. Rev. Summers McGavock died 12 January 1984.
Ezra Summers McGavock and his brother Cecil Billups became embroiled in a bitter legal dispute over the settlement of their mother's land at Dutch Gap farm near Richmond, Virginia. Correspondence of Randal McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Cecil Billups McGavock, Ezra Summers McGavock, and Mary Haynes McGavock shed light on this divisive argument.
Scope and Content
The Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers are arranged in four series, comprising correspondence, financial and legal records, records pertaining to the settlement and management of the estate of Cealy Billups, and miscellaneous records.
Series I, Correspondence (1884-1964), consists of letters sent and/or received by Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and his family. Correspondence include Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and his wife Amanda Billups McGavock and their son Randal McGavock, Cecil Billups McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr., and Ezra Summers McGavock. Also contains in this series are letters of Mamie Claiborne McGavock (Mrs. Cecil Billups McGavock) and Mary Haynes McGavock (Mrs. Ezra Summers McGavock). Topics discussed include agriculture, animal husbandry, politics, and family life and illness.
Extensive correspondence concerning real estate investments in Norfolk, Virginia, Nashville, Tennessee, and Wythe County are also included. Correspondence of Cecil Billups McGavock contains many letters discussing school life at Emory and Henry College and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Similarly, the correspondence of Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. covers his student days at Massanutten Academy in Woodstock, Virginia, S. R. Crocketts school in Crockett, Virginia, and Fishburne Military Academy in Waynesboro, Virginia.
Series II, Financial and Legal Records (1899-1932), includes account statements and notices from the Bank of Max Meadows, the Bank of Wytheville, and the First National Bank of Wytheville. Also included in this series are livestock market reports (1917-1929), bills and receipts (1899-1932, undated), and tax receipts (1901-1932).
Series III, Cealy Billups Estate Records (1910-1929), contains records pertaining to the settlement and management of the estate of Norfolk, Virginia businessman Cealy Billups. His daughter, Amanda Billups McGavock, inherited several residential and commercial properties in Norfolk; these properties were directly managed by various real estate and rental agencies. Records and statements of these agencies (1911-1929), bills and receipts (1911-1928, undated), Norfolk Water Department receipts (1911-1929), and tax receipts (1911-1912) comprise this series. Also included is a copy of Cealy Billups' will and distribution of his estate.
Series IV, Miscellaneous Records (1909-1933, undated), includes a livestock insurance certificate dated 1929, report cards of Ezra Summers McGavock from Hampden-Sydney College dated 1919, and other items.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence. 1896-1932., 36 folders
  - Folder 1. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.. 1896-1905., 13 items. (Series-folder 1:1)
    Correspondents include: Edmund Pendleton, James A. Walker, Humphreys-Davidson Hardware Company, J. G. Brown of Bank of Wytheville, A. G. Crockett of Max Meadows Pharmacy, S. R. Crockett, J. V. Haller, R. H. Glendy, William W. Brauer, and W. G. Heuse.
  - Folder 2. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1906-1907., 11 items. (Series-folder 1:2)
    Correspondents include: Alice M. Howard, Lee & Company of Lynchburg, Virginia, D. D. Hull Jr. of Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company, T. A. Groseclose of Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company, J. Norment Powell, Princeton Banking Company, and Robert Blair.
  - Folder 3. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1908-1910., 8 items. (Series-folder 1:3)
    Correspondents include: J. A. Howard, C. W. Gleaves of First National Bank of Wytheville, L. D. Calfee, Robert Sayers Jr., and Tuttle and Clark Company.
  - Folder 4. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1911., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:4)
    Correspondents include Clyde Smith, Ferdinand Powell, William J. Brown, H. C. Hoggard and Company, Williams, Hayes and Company, and W. W. Vicar of Norfolk Bank for Savings and Trusts.
  - Folder 5. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.. January-February 1912.., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:5)
    Correspondents include: Norfolk National Bank, W. W. Vicar of Norfolk Bank for Savings and Trusts, Leland Jordan of Murfreesboro Bank and Trust Company, C. W. Coleman, Williams, Hayes and Company, and Jesse Beery.
  - Folder 6. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. March-December 1912., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:6)
    Correspondents include: C. b. Welton, L. E. Harvie of Real Estate Loan Deposit Company, R. B. Chaffin and Company, Julien Gunn, Williams, Hayes and Company, B. E. Smith, and Harding A. Jackson.
  - Folder 7. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. January-June 1913., 11 item. (Series-folder 1:7)
    Harding A. Jackson, Julien Gunn, R. B. Chaffin and Company, L. E. Harvie of Real Estate Loan Deposit Company, and H. M. Hayes of Williams, Hayes and Company.
  - Folder 8. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. July-December 1913., 8 items. (Series-folder 1:8)
    Correspondents include: H. M. Hayes of Williams, Hayes, and Company, W. P. James, Colby N. Thomas, Douglas E. Taylor, and W. S. Sayers.
  - Folder 9. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1914., 6 items. (Series-folder 1:9)
    Correspondents include: L. E. Harvie of F. W. Dabney Realty Corporation, John S. Childrey, and R. B. Chaffin and Company, P. M. Berry of Middle Atlantic Immigration Company, A. M. Gwyn, and Annie Sayers.
  - Folder 10. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1915-1916., 15 items. (Series-folder 1:10)
    Correspondents include: Randal McGavock, J. S. Crockett, S. F. Ewald Company, E. Crittendon, Charles Tunstall Real Estate, Trust and Insurance Company, Kirkpatrick and Howard Company, Williams, Hayes and
  - Folder 11. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1917., 11 items. (Series-folder 1:11)
    Barrett and Hurd Inc., J. S. Crockett, L. E. Harvie of Broadway Realty Company, Randal McGavock, W. S. Poage, W. W. Dillon and Company, M. P. Barrett of Barrett and Hurd Company, and S. G. Hudson.
  - Folder 12. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1918-1919., 10 items. (Series-folder 1:12)
    Correspondents include: N. R. Patrick, T. K. Wolfe of Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Bennett Land and Company, Jno. A. Bolling of W. W. Dillon and Company, J. M. Corvair, L. D. Walder of W. S. Robinson and Company, Charles M. Langhorne of Fish Guano Company, and Henry Sweets of Presbyterian Church in the United States.
  - Folder 13. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1920-1921., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:13)
    Correspondents include: J. M. Corvair, James M. Graham of Bank of Max Meadows, Robert Sayers, C. A. Moomaw of Mountain Trust Bank, J. P. Wade of Kerns Commission Company, and B. E. Smith of Church Hill Bank.
  - Folder 14. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1922-1925., 6 items. (Series-folder 1:14)
    Correspondents include Randal McGavock, L. A. Hull of National Carbide Sales Corporation, Stras, Stras and Persinger Realtors, and Barnett-Schenk drug Company Inc.
  - Folder 15. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1926., 15 items. (Series-folder 1:15)
    Correspondents include: James M. Graham of Bank of Max Meadows, John t. Howe, L. B. Davis of Mountain Trust Bank, Newton and Company, J. M. Wade of Kerns Commission Company, Edward J. Fox of Live Stock Commission Merchants, Mary McGavock, and W. G. Porter.
  - Folder 16. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1927-1929. (Series-folder 1:16)
    Correspondents include: Randal McGavock, John T. Howe and Company, Ezra Summers McGavock, Fannie Harvie, Florence B. Chandler, Harvie Realtors, L. B. Davis of Mountain Trust Bank, Mary McGavock, and Holcombe Robertson.
  - Folder 17. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. 1930-1932., 6 items. (Series-folder 1:17)
    Correspondents include: W. L. Clayton of Jelliffe, Wright and Company, Fannie Harvie, Ezra Summers McGavock, L. E. Harvie, and Cecil H. McGavock.
  - Folder 18. Correspondence - Amanda Billups McGavock. 1884-1910., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:18)
    Correspondents include: Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., S. F. Ewald, J. G. Brown of Bank of Wytheville, and Ezra Summers McGavock.
  - Folder 19. Correspondence - Amanda Billups McGavock. 1911-1914., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:19)
    Correspondents include: W. W. Vicar of Norfolk Bank for Saving and Trusts and H. C. Hoggard and Company.
  - Folder 20. Correspondence - Cecil Billups McGavock. 1906-1907., 11 items. (Series-folder 1:20)
    Correspondents include: Nancy Hanson, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Virginia D. Watkins, Annie F. Crockett, and Amanda Billups McGavock.
  - Folder 21. Correspondence - Cecil Billups McGavock. 1908-1924, undated., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:21)
    Correspondents include: M. H. Claiborne, Randal McGavock, C. Kent, J. C. Drewry and Company, Holcombe Robertson, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Harvie Realtors, and Amanda Billups McGavock.
  - Folder 22. Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock. 1911 - February 1912., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:22)
    Correspondents include: Cecil Billups McGavock, Nena C. Hager, M. H. Claiborne, Mrs. Royall R. Claiborne, and Royall R. Claiborne.
  - Folder 23. Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock. March-April 1912., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:23)
    Correspondents include: Blanche D. Ambler, M. H. Claiborne, Anne Bolling, Amanda Billups McGavock, M. H. Claiborne, and Mrs. Royall R. Claiborne.
  - Folder 24. Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock. July - October 1912., 15 items. (Series-folder 1:24)
    Correspondents include: Mrs. Royall R. Claiborne, Cecil Billups McGavock, and Nena C. Hager.
  - Folder 25. Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock. November 1912 - 1926, undated., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:25)
    Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, Cecil Billups McGavock, Nena C. Hager, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Ernest Walton Browne, Czarina F. Pettit, Thomas H. Wilcox, and Edgar Cecil Andrew.
  - Folder 26. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. 1911 - January 1912., 8 items. (Series-folder 1:26)
    Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, T. Graham Crockett, Randal McGavock, and Robert Blair.
  - Folder 27. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. February - March 1912., 8 items. (Series-folder 1:27)
    Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock and Agnes Simmerman.
  - Folder 28. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. September 1912., 6 items. (Series-folder. 1:28)
    Correspondents include: Randal McGavock, Mamie Claiborne McGavock, Amanda Billups McGavock, and Cecil Billups McGavock.
  - Folder 29. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. October 1912., 13 items. (Series-folder 1:29)
    Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, Agnes Simmerman, and Randal McGavock.
  - Folder 30. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. November 1912., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:30)
    Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, Randal McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., and Agnes Simmerman.
  - Folder 31. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. December 1912., 7 items. (Series-folder 1:31)
    Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock and Sallie Green.
  - Folder 32. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. 1914-1917., 10 items. (Series-folder 1:32)
    Correspondents include: Mamie Claiborne McGavock, Randal McGavock, and Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
  - Folder 33. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. 1918-1920., 14 items. (Series-folder 1:33)
    Correspondents include: Ellen Simmerman and Randal McGavock.
  - Folder 34. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. 1921-1936., 9 items. (Series-folder 1:34)
    Correspondents include: Ellen Simmerman, Stuart B. Campbell, Cecil Billups McGavock, Rachel M. Ewing, Randal McGavock, W. A. Kegley, and Cecil Billups McGavock Jr.
  - Folder 35. Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. 1937, 1964, undated., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:35)
    Correspondents include: Cecil Billups McGavock, E. Lee Trinkle, W. C. Thomas of Wythe County National Farm Loan Association, W. E. Davidson, James W. Patton, Andrew G. McLeary of Dixieland Equipment Company, Randal D. McGavock, Herschel Gower, George Waller Crockett, Agnes Simmerman, and Ellen Simmerman.
  - Folder 36. Correspondence - Miscellaneous. 1912-1937., 3 items. (Series-folder 1:36)
    Correspondents include: Royall R. Claiborne to Nena Hager, R. A. Lampton to James O'Conner, and E. Lee Trinkle to Cynthia Painter McGavock
- Series II. Financial and Legal Records. 1899-1932., 9 folders.
- Series III. Cealy Billups Estate Records. 1910-1929., 8 folders.
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Records. 1909-1933., 1 folder.